<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Code | Strangely Specific and Very Odd]]></title>
  <link href="http://Gastove.github.io/blog/categories/code/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://Gastove.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-08-11T16:50:35-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://Gastove.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ross M. Donaldson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Correcting Text Alignment for Gists in Octopress Themes]]></title>
    <link href="http://Gastove.github.io/blog/2013/08/11/correcting-text-alignment-for-gists-in-octopress-themes/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-11T15:19:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://Gastove.github.io/blog/2013/08/11/correcting-text-alignment-for-gists-in-octopress-themes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So I’m setting up my hella sweet Octopress blog and I’m feeling pretty sharp and I decide it’s time for a theme. What could be better! Gussy the place up a bit. There are <a href="https://github.com/imathis/octopress/wiki/3rd-Party-Octopress-Themes">bunches of themes</a> available, so that bit was pretty simple. Installation: boom! Previews: bam! All exactly as easy as advertised. </p>

<p>To celebrate, I decide to publish my first github gist. </p>

<p>And all the text aligns center.</p>

<p>…</p>

<p>Okay so I have no idea why anybody would ever, ever do that, but the answer seems to go like so: there’s an SCSS template in <code>sass/parts</code> called <code>_article.scss</code>. It contains a CSS entry, so (many things removed for brevity):</p>

<div><table class="CodeRay"><tr>
  <td class="line-numbers" title="double click to toggle" ondblclick="with (this.firstChild.style) { display = (display == '') ? 'none' : '' }"><pre><a href="#n1" name="n1">1</a>
<a href="#n2" name="n2">2</a>
<a href="#n3" name="n3">3</a>
<a href="#n4" name="n4">4</a>
<a href="#n5" name="n5">5</a>
<a href="#n6" name="n6">6</a>
<a href="#n7" name="n7">7</a>
<a href="#n8" name="n8">8</a>
<a href="#n9" name="n9">9</a>
<strong><a href="#n10" name="n10">10</a></strong>
<a href="#n11" name="n11">11</a>
<a href="#n12" name="n12">12</a>
<a href="#n13" name="n13">13</a>
<a href="#n14" name="n14">14</a>
<a href="#n15" name="n15">15</a>
<a href="#n16" name="n16">16</a>
<a href="#n17" name="n17">17</a>
</pre></td>
  <td class="code"><pre> article{
    .entry-content{
        table{
            background: $color-gray04;
            border: 1px solid $color-gray03;
            border-spacing: 0;
            margin-top: 10px;
            th{
                background: $color-gray03;
                padding: 0 15px;
            }
            td{
                text-align: center;
            }
        }
    }
}
</pre></td>
</tr></table>
</div>

<p>That little td definition is the one that gets you, and here’s a thing that threw me off for a bit: this same file exists (almost identically) inside <code>.themes/[Your Theme Name]/sass/parts/</code> – and changing the theme-specific file does <em>not</em> override the stuff in <code>[Blog]/sass/parts</code>. Only tweaking the top-level definiton put my gist back over to the left. </p>

<p>I’m pretty much a CSS n00b, so it’s entirely likely there’s something derpy I’m doing/not getting with this. If any Octopress ninjas out in Blogland have a clearer idea of what’s going on than I do, <em>please</em>… oh wait. This theme doesn’t support comments. </p>

<p>Tweet at me. That’s it. <a href="http://www.twitter.com/Gastove">With this handy link</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pure Show-And-Tell: My First Gist]]></title>
    <link href="http://Gastove.github.io/blog/2013/08/11/pure-show-and-tell-my-first-gist/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-11T10:53:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://Gastove.github.io/blog/2013/08/11/pure-show-and-tell-my-first-gist</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>And now, a barefaced excuse to muck about with Octopress markdown and plugins. Presenting: my first gist. Do you care? The whole works (and some verbiage) after the cut.</p>

<!--more-->

<p>While ambling about the internet trying to style my schamncy new web page, I did two things, one clever and one not: </p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Clever</strong>: I realized I didn’t want to write my own CSS sheets, because fuck that noise.</li>
  <li><strong>Not-So-Much</strong>: I forgot about Twitter Bootstrap. </li>
</ul>

<p>I found the pleasing, if peculiar, <a href="www.getskeleton.com">Skeleton.css</a> – which is nice looking and open source and free, and rescales (reasonably) well on mobile. Only problem: the provided page template is in straight HTML, and I’m writing in Scalate’s implementation of Jade (itself a reduction of Scaml, which is Scala Haml. Oye.) So, I re-wrote the thing. Maybe this will help another person, ever? (Yeah, I think it’s a funny line too.)</p>

<h3 id="the-gist">The Gist</h3>
<p><div><script src='https://gist.github.com/6201942.js'></script>
<noscript><pre><code></code></pre></noscript></div>
</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
